<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Whiskypedia Reviews</title>
  <subtitle>Real Reviews for Real People</subtitle>
  <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews.html"/>
  <link rel="self" href="http://whiskypedia.ca/feeds/reviews.xml"/>
  
  <updated>2012-04-27T21:22:00-02:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Steven Smolinski</name>
  </author>
  <contributor>
    <name>Aaron</name>
  </contributor>
  <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews.html</id>
  <logo>/apple-touch-icon-57x57-precomposed.png</logo>
  <rights>Copyright 2012 Steven Smolinski</rights>

  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Glen Arran Port Finish Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/glen-arran-port-finish.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/glen-arran-port-finish.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-27T21:22:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting malt to try because there aren&#39;t a lot of port cask finished single malts out there. It&#39;s part of Glen Arran&#39;s line of finishes with no age statement and among them the port finish has to be the oddest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it&#39;s a pinky salmon colour. You don&#39;t realize how much it&#39;s taken for granted that a single malt should be some shade of orange, until it&#39;s not. I looked the bottle over for damage or an expiry date to make sure I got the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colour aside, this malt packs a punch. It&#39;s semi-cask strength at 50%, but not too harsh to drink straight up. And the port finish adds enough flavour to keep up with the alcohol content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what about that finish? Port sweetens the malt like sherry, but it doesn&#39;t taste like sherry. The port finish has a more tart, grapey flavour to it. I can promise there&#39;s no finish like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s an acquired taste. Sherried malts are a dime a dozen, and the more sherried, the less distinctive they are. But this port finish is unique and interesting, if not very familiar. Unfortunately, it&#39;s unique and interesting because of the &lt;em&gt;finish&lt;/em&gt;, rather than the malt itself. Like sherry, the port takes over the malt, and it becomes all about the finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there&#39;s a real shame in that. Glen Arran produces some of the best tasting young malts sold, all without having to drown them in the flavour of some other spirit. The port finish is good because Glen Arran seems incapable of releasing a poor malt, but it&#39;s still a gimmick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s not to say it&#39;s not worth buying. If you&#39;re interested in odd finishes slightly off the beaten path, you will enjoy this one.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Auchentoshan 18 Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/auchentoshan-18.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/auchentoshan-18.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-26T20:40:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Auchentoshan is the quintessential lowland malt. The 10 year old has graced the LCBO shelves regularly for years. Unpeated lowlands are generally more delicate than your chest-hair growing Islay malts, so Auchentoshan has been a fantastic gift for ages, especially as an introductory single malt for blend drinkers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nose is weak. You have to stick your nose way down into the glass, and then all it offers up is your typical lowland fare: grassy citrus. It gets richer once you’ve had a sip. There’s nothing really distinctive here that you won’t find in another bottling of Auchentoshan, and probably for cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also spicier up front than your typical 18 year old. Relatively tame after half a glass, but still surprising. While starting relatively oily and warming, the blast of “spice” (i.e., burning) dominates the otherwise subtle sweet lemongrass flavour. Water is mandatory to bring out the more delicate flavour.  It pushes any burning off to late into the finish, which means you enjoy each sip for longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finish has a splash of the salty sea air that you get in larger quantities in an Islay malt like a Bowmore. It’s subtle, but there’s so little going on otherwise that it’s notable.  Bowmore owns Auchentoshan, so while they’re hundreds of miles apart, and made in completely separate ways, it’s interesting that they have some tiny thread in common.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Balvenie 12 Doublewood Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/balvenie-12-doublewood.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/balvenie-12-doublewood.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-26T18:45:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Balvenie is one of the oldest single malt distilleries still producing from the Speyside. It resides in Dufftown, sharing the town with many other famous distilleries such as Glenfiddich. Balvenie malts are generally floral and very sweet, and with the Doublewood advertising its sherry-cask finish, this malt holds true to that reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nose is just a sherry-like sweetness. If you want to find something else, go ahead, but we can&#39;t find it. It’s just nicely sweet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are probably the traditional flowery and citrus flavours in there somewhere, but they’re overwhelmed by the sweetness. It’s smooth for a 12-year old, which is also a nice characteristic of many Speysides. Sherry cask finishes stay for a while, and this is no different. It’s long, sweet, and satisfying. It’s a nice warming malt for a cold evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water takes all the molasses and sherry flavours out. It’s still sweet, but lighter, like honey. The finish isn’t quite as strong, but it’s still relatively long and enjoyable. But if you want a Speyside without all the sherry, you can buy a whole bottle of something else rather than diluting it out of this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a solid Speyside malt, with its flowery undertones, and sherry dominating the nose and flavour. The Balvenie shares this niche with Macallan, Aberlour, and other characteristic Speyside single malts.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Glenlivet 12 Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/glenlivet-12.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/glenlivet-12.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-26T17:26:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For many people, the Glenlivet is often a bridge between blended malt whiskey and single malts. Its smooth, consistent and subtle flavours make this a great introduction to single malt whiskey. This has made Glenlivet one of the most recognized single malt names in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nose on the 12 is sweet, but lighter and more delicate than a Bourbon’s sweetness. It’s not sugary like molasses. Speyside malts like Glenlivet are known for their subtle flavours and aromatic, almost flowery nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Glienlivet’s primary flavour is a slightly sweet vanilla. It starts very smooth with almost nothing but vanilla, and then builds.  A bit of bite to it, but certainly no more than any other 12 year old.  The finish is short, and has a characteristic maltiness.  It finishes more like a dry wine than a brandy.
Water takes out any bite, but leaves the character of the malt untouched.  It still is primarily vanilla and malty smoothness, just moreso.  Delicate malts are usually erased by water, losing all distinctiveness.  While the nose is wiped out, the Glenlivet’s trademark vanilla and smooth maltiness come into their own with a drop or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many beginners start with the Glenlivet, and for good reason.  Beginners should take note: this is a good, gentle introduction to the pleasure of single malts.  It can remain a favourite, even when moving on to more distinctive malts.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bowmore Tempest</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/bowmore-tempest-10.html"/>
    
    <author><name>Steve</name></author>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/bowmore-tempest-10.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-13T19:28:03-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bowmore malts are some of the smoothest Islay malts going.  They&#39;re known for combining a beautiful smoothness with almost shocking flavours of phenol, peat smoke, and saltiness.  This malt is a cask strength, coming in at 56%, so expect a bit of rough ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nose has less salt and sea air than you&#39;d expect in a Bowmore.  It&#39;s deceptively subtle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This malt has warming, smooth malty tastes that turn to smoky, peaty saltiness when you swallow.  It&#39;s wonderfully integrated.  The finish is long and all peat smoke.  It&#39;s slightly less salty than some regular production Bowmores.  But it&#39;s also more warming, and coats your throat like a cask strength malt should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water reduces the initial burst of flavour, but keeps the essential character.  The finish is still long and peaty.  The flavours are still relatively complex.  Water it down if the cask strength alcohol percentage is too bitey, but this malt is very drinkable straight up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bowmore consistently bottles good experiences. They&#39;re a cornerstone of the Islay experience.  They&#39;re integrated and smooth, all while putting some hair on your chest.  This is no different, and will reward and malt enthusiast with a taste for Islay and cask strength malts.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Aberlour A'bunadh Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/aberlour-abunadh.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/aberlour-abunadh.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-08T15:00:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A&#39;bunadh is gaelic for &#34;of the origin&#34;. We&#39;ve taken to amiably calling this malt &#34;Origin&#34;. Aberlour&#39;s made a brilliant no-age-statement, sherry finished cask strength powershouse (60.4% alcohol in this batch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing you notice about this malt is the deep reddish brown colour.  It&#39;s darker and redder than almost any malt on the market. The nose is dominated by all the sherry cask elements: molasses, sugar, and sweetness.  The more subtle traces are still &#34;big&#34; flavours: dark fruits like black cherry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 60% alcohol, this is going to pack a punch, no matter what you do.  Aberlour has jammed such strength of flavour in the remaining 40% that they manage to take over from the pure alcohol, and give the malt a life beyond the initial burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most distinctive part of this malt is that the inherent flavours of the malt are not over-powered by the alcohol content. Cask strength malts are valued by enthusiasts because the malt is close to the pure level of the cask. For modern production bottles, the bottler has already diluted the malt with water to 40%, but not cask strength malts. They retain the original characteristic of the malt straight from the cask.  The trade-off is that you usually cut the malt with water to your own taste. A seasoned scotch drinker can enjoy Origin uncut, although we do recommend you do so with care. It hits like a truck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding water makes this malt dangerously good. If you add enough water to reduce the alcohol content down to normal levels, the drink becomes more tractable. Both the intense flavour and the burn are relieved, but in good proportion: it&#39;s a smoother drink where the sweet, big flavours still overwhelm any trace of alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finish is long and warming. It is a perfect winter malt because of the warming. Any trace of burn disappears, and it leaves a sweet, warm bit of comfort that radiates down the throat. It&#39;s a brandy experience, leaving you with a glow that lasts a few minutes with each sip.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Talisker 10 Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/talisker-10.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/talisker-10.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-07T10:00:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Islay-like with some extra sweetness. Big, salty, peaty, and wonderfully complex. This is a must-try malt that will put some hair on your chest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nose is mainly peat smoke, leather, sea air. You&#39;ll smell it well before the glass gets to your nose. This is not some delicate Speyside you have to stick your nose in the glass to smell. It&#39;s a blast of phenolic sea air. Much like an Islay. Which isn&#39;t surprising since it&#39;s made on the Isle of Skye, just north of Islay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sip is a fireball of flavours. It&#39;s a ten-year old, so expect an initial spiciness before you settle into it. But the flavours are big all the way to the end of the glass. The flavour has a syrupy sweetness, and malty taste that&#39;s hard to hold onto, since your nose will register the salt and peat smoke. It&#39;s a very complex malt, as every sip will go through all these stages of development. The smokiness and sea air come through the nose, and last forever. You&#39;re not going to kiss your wife right after a taste of this malt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water dilutes the nose and the initial spiciness. It becomes a sweeter drink and keeps the long finish of smoke and sea air. It&#39;s a milder way to get that long finish. But it&#39;s also loses some of the complexity of the development, so we prefer this malt without the water.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Aberlour 10 Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/aberlour-10.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/aberlour-10.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-06T11:40:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re looking for a straightforward Speyside malt with strong expressions of vanilla and sherry, this is a great choice with a great price tag. It&#39;s not sophisticated like other Speysides, but it&#39;s warm and comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nose is sweet like bourbon, but not a sherry bomb. It has a medium body, but medium in a good way. Sweet without being too sweet. Long lasting but not oily. Medium in the way of being balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not a fan of saying that there are &#34;hints of&#34; anything, since that&#39;s usually code for a tasting snob. Like: &#34;hints of tulip petals&#34; or &#34;hints of Paris in the spring&#34;. But this malt has hints of vanilla. Not an outright flavour, more like a reminder of vanilla. This is common in bourbon casked malts, and this particular malt is a good expression of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dominant flavours are vanilla, sherry and a mild spiciness. Without water, the sherry gets in the way of the more subtle flavours that you find in Speyside malt. The delicate floral flavours might be in there, but it&#39;s too hidden with the bitey character of any 10-year old and the sweetness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water takes most of the sweet out of it, but leaves the bare malt. It isn&#39;t replaced with flowers that you&#39;d expect from a more sophisticated Speyside. This malt doesn&#39;t need any water, and it doesn&#39;t help. Drink this straight up and enjoy it for what it is.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Glenrothes 1994 Review</title>
    <link href="http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/glenrothes-1994.html"/>
    
    <id>http://whiskypedia.ca/reviews/glenrothes-1994.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-06T11:40:00-02:30</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Glenrothes malts are generally admired by experienced scotch drinkers. The distillery puts out solid bottlings every few years, following an unusual pattern of listing the year the malt was made, rather than the number of years it was aged. This particular malt was made in 1994, but bottled in 2006, making it a twelve year old vintage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nose has malt, vanilla and a little butterscotch in the background. It’s well balanced — no one overshadows the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First sip, there is more than a little burning. But once you soldier past, you’ll find floral notes intermixed with a vanilla and chocolate. The finish is mid to long with a little ginger-like burn to remind you of that first sip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a complex malt. We try to name the really dominant flavour, but some malts are just well integrated amongst their flavours. Bowmore is a good example from Islay, and Glenrothes is a nicely well balanced Speyside malt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glenrothes will always have a 12-year old out, even if it’s not this particular 12 year old. As a rule, they’re a treat to an experienced drinker who wants something more complex in the Speyside flavour than a Glenfiddich.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  

</feed>
